<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Rhys Powell</title>
 <link href="http://frogbot.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://frogbot.github.com/"/>
 <updated>2011-11-20T19:49:10+11:00</updated>
 <id>http://frogbot.github.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Rhys Powell</name>
   <email>rhys@rpowell.me</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Thoughts on the iPad 2</title>
   <link href="http://frogbot.github.com/2011/12/01/ipad-2.html"/>
   <updated>2011-12-01T00:00:00+11:00</updated>
   <id>http://frogbot.github.com/2011/12/01/ipad-2</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Thoughts on the iPad 2&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I recently picked up an iPad, having barely used one outside of a store before this point. I had my vague notions of what it was like to use, based of brief encounters in store displays and the one or two times I saw people using them out in the wild, but other than that I was totally inexperienced in using it. What follows is a somewhat brief summary of my thoughts on it so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick note before we get started, the specific model I bought was the black iPad 2 with 16GB of storage space (about 14GB once formatted and with iOS loaded on) and Wi-Fi. I can't see the experience changing much based on how much storage space you have available, but 3G seems like it would have an effect on how  and where the iPad is used. So keep that in mind while reading my review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also I'm an iPhone owner, so I've had experience with iOS before this point, and I also own a Mac and use much of the same software there as I've been using on my iPad. With that out of the way, let's talk about the iPad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Hardware&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing that stands out about the iPad is just how &lt;em&gt;solid&lt;/em&gt; it feels; the buttons have a nice click to them, the devices edges feel rounded to perfection and the whole thing just has that feel of Apple quality. Also the device has a wonderfully simple profile, with it's buttons and ports al lhidden around the back edge, looking at it straight on all you see is a bordered black rectangle with rounded corners. I have to wonder just how much thought was given to every aspect of the iPad's industrial design, it's truly wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://f.cl.ly/items/3z1E432o2B253l3k0f2p/IMG_0003.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing I've noted is just how good its battery life is, it easily gets 10 hours of battery when I'm just reading and writing on it. Games tend to drain it more rapidly but even then it beats my MacBook handily. I've never owned a device with a battery this good, no longer do I have to worry about how charged the battery is, lowering brightness and obsessively killing background apps. It's really quite a liberating experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another surprise is just how easy it is to type on. Propped up with the smart cover to put it on a good angle, I can happily type on it at quite a reasonable speed, about 80% of my speed on a regular keyboard. Of course I still prefer a proper keyboard where I can get it but the iPad is more than good enough for taking notes on or drafting an essay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://api.cld.me/AQub/IMG_0003.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the big additions with the iPad 2 was its cameras, a VGA camera on the front and a slightly more capable camera capable of 720p video on the back. Neither of these cameras is great, although more than adequate for video chat, where it's gotten the most use by me. The quality of the rear camera tends to fall flat in anything but bright direct light, but I guess it's better than nothing. I'm honestly curious to know how many of the people that complained about the original iPad not having a camera would use the camera on the iPad 2o often, not many I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://f.cl.ly/items/3C3C2M2S1X1W1M0D2X04/IMG_0008.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the actual display deserves a mention. It's wonderful not quite as good as the Retina display on the iPhone 4 but easily a close second. Colours are bright and vivid, even compared to my iPhone and MacBook's screen. Since the iPad is almost entirely comprised of this display it makes sense that they'd invest in the best on the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Software&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After being accustomed to using iOS on the iPhones 3.5 inch display for so long, seeing it blown up to a 10 inch display is initially quite odd. Everything is just a bit bigger, more spaced out, giving text and images more room to breath. Going back to the iPhone after using the iPad for extended periods of time feels comparatively cramped, almost suffocating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://f.cl.ly/items/2Y2C0q1L3h241h3N2W14/Image%202011.09.26%202:49:31%20PM.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://f.cl.ly/items/2Y2C0q1L3h241h3N2W14/Image%202011.09.26%202:49:31%20PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing to note, iOS seems less portrait oriented on the iPad. That's not to say it's landscape oriented&lt;a href=&quot;Although&quot;&gt;^1&lt;/a&gt;, the iPad doesn't seem at all concerned with which way you hold it. Almost every app on the iPad works in both orientations, even the home screen and lock screen. It happily adapts to whichever way you hold it. That said I've found portrait to be more suited to reading while landscape gets used more when I'm typing  or watching video. Hell, the iPad doesn't even care if you hold it upside down, something I often found myself doing unintentionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://api.cld.me/ARYE/Image_2011.09.26_2_57_10_PM.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://api.cld.me/ARYE/Image_2011.09.26_2_57_10_PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main ways apps take advantage of the screen, especially in landscape, is by showing more levels of the navigation heirachy at once. Take the above screenshot of Instapaper, in the iPhone app, the left sidebar is all that is initially shown when a user launches the app. The user selects a  folder and then is shown the right view, filling the screen. In the iPad app however, the user can be shown both views at once when they're in landscape, allowing for easier navigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've also noticed that the iPad tends to lend itself better to creating things than the iPhone. I'm already heavily using a lot of content creation apps, from Writing Kit and OmniOutliner to Apple's own iWork suite. The larger keyboard really does make the iPad far better than the iPhone in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact the more I use the iPad, the more I see it as just another computer, albeit one less conventional than the norm.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Joy of Text</title>
   <link href="http://frogbot.github.com/2011/11/11/joy-of-text.html"/>
   <updated>2011-11-11T00:00:00+11:00</updated>
   <id>http://frogbot.github.com/2011/11/11/joy-of-text</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;The Joy of Text&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's something to be said for the simple plain text file, over the past 40 years or so computing has changed immensely, yet the plain text file has stood still. This simple, enduring means of conveying information is one of the most flexible tools in computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A Little Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you a story about a program called &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microsoft_OneNote&quot;&gt;Microsoft OneNote&lt;/a&gt;, a note taking tool from Microsoft that's been bundled with new copies of Office for the past few years. Now, I'm not going to beat on OneNote, in fact I think it's a pretty good program from a utility and usability format, but it has one major flaw which I'll get to in a minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I really liked OneNote back when I used to use it, it was a great note taking tool and I used it for a lot of my subject notes in high school. It allowed me to easily organise notes, diagrams and other clippings into freeform 'notebooks' and served as a pretty good organisational tool, it was a really neat piece of software. To achieve all this cool functionality, it stored all the user's data in a proprietary &lt;code&gt;.one&lt;/code&gt; format. A weird mix of XML and image files globbed together into a single binary file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this worked fine for a while, I was the only one editing these files and I didn't have to worry about using them on other platforms because I only used Windows. Everything worked fine for a long time, but then a big change happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Changing Platforms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'd been getting really into web development with &lt;a href=&quot;http://rubyonrails.org/&quot;&gt;Ruby on Rails&lt;/a&gt;, which really doesn't work that well on Windows. I'd been dual booting Windows 7 and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ubuntu.com/&quot;&gt;Ubuntu Linux&lt;/a&gt; (eventually switching to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.archlinux.org/&quot;&gt;Arch Linux&lt;/a&gt;). I coded in Linux and did pretty much everything else in Windows, it worked &lt;em&gt;okay&lt;/em&gt;, but it was hardly ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also around this time I participated in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.computing.unsw.edu.au/progcomp/&quot;&gt;local university's programming competition&lt;/a&gt;, we made it into the finals and had to bring our own computer along. The only laptop our team had between us was my friend's MacBook Pro, so we used that. I like it, I mean I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; liked it, so much so that I started saving for my own and later that year picked up the MacBook Pro that I'm writing this post on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings us back to OneNote. As it turns out, there's no version of OneNote for OS X, so I had no way of reading all those notes I'd spent untold hours compiling. Needless to say I was a little pissed off, I'd been burned for the first time by proprietary formats and I wasn't going to let it happen again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Plain Text&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That brings us back to my original point about, pretty much every computer on earth can read plain text. It's also a really flexible format, you can express a lot in plain text. But you're probably shaking your head at this point thinking &quot;you must be joking, plain text can't be formatted at all, it's utterly primitive!&quot; Hopefully this post will change your mind about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why Use Plain Text?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plain text files have a lot of benefits over other formats, chiefly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They're portable&lt;/strong&gt;, with few exceptions every computer on earth is capable of reading plain text files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They're tiny&lt;/strong&gt;, the size of most text files can be measured in bytes, there's no bloated headers or storage formats here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can probably already edit them&lt;/strong&gt;, every computer I've ever had has built in tools for working with text files, no software to install and pay for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They're durable&lt;/strong&gt;, 40 years from now, you'll still be able to open and edit your text files with ease, which is more than can be said for the latest incarnation of the &lt;code&gt;.doc&lt;/code&gt; format.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So now you know &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; using plain text is a good idea, let's look at the how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tools for Working With Plain Text&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now plain text is only as useful as the tools you use with it. On it's own plain text can be fairly primitive, but there's a lot you can do to really make the most of this format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Markdown&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; is the plain text formatting syntax invented by John Gruber of &lt;a href=&quot;http://daringfireball.net/&quot;&gt;Daring Fireball&lt;/a&gt;. What's that mean exactly? Well the basic idea is that you use a certain formatting style when writing your text files which allows you to apply formatting to otherwise unformatted text files. Here's an example of some of the stuff you can do with Markdown&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# This is a heading #

You can format text with *italics* and make it **bold**.

You can do bulleted list:

+ One
+ Two
+ Three
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, even without converting this text to HTML, a Word document or some other format, it's already pretty readable as-is. That's one of the great things about Markdown, it takes conventions that people already used in plain text emails and bulletin board systems and makes them convention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;NValt&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://cdn2.brettterpstra.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/nvALT2.0Screenshot.jpg?9d7bd4&quot; alt=&quot;NVAlt, a lightning fast, lightweight note taking tool&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://brettterpstra.com/project/nvalt/&quot;&gt;NValt&lt;/a&gt; is a super fast note taking tool for Mac OS X with built in support for Markdown. I have literally hundreds of notes managed by NValt, all of which are stored as plain text files on my computer. It allows me to show a Markdown preview for any of my notes and offers a metric ton of other features like fullscreen support, full text search and custom colour schemes and fonts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Simplenote&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://simplenoteapp.com/&quot;&gt;Simplenote&lt;/a&gt; is an iOS app and website that allows you to store plain text notes in the cloud. It has a some very cool features including the ability to reverse changes to notes. It also integrates effortlessly with NValt allowing me to access notes made on my Mac from my iOS devices and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How I Use These Tools&lt;/h3&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Limits</title>
   <link href="http://frogbot.github.com/2011/10/09/limits.html"/>
   <updated>2011-10-09T00:00:00+11:00</updated>
   <id>http://frogbot.github.com/2011/10/09/limits</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In writing &lt;em&gt;The Cat in the Hat&lt;/em&gt;, Dr. Seuss was tasked with creating a book composed solely of the 348 words that his friend William Ellsworth Spaulding believed they should developmentally know. Out of these he made use of 223 words on the list and only 13 that were not. Soon following this, Seuss was challenged by Random House, his publisher, to create a book using a vocabulary of only 50 words, betting hime $50 that he couldn't do it. Seuss won the bet, publishing the bizarre, delightful and somewhat repetitve &lt;em&gt;Green Eggs and Ham&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lego has long touted that with six standard two-by-four stud Lego bricks, you can create somewhere in the vicinity of ten-million different combinations, quite an impressive number to say the least. But this is an understatement, in his academic paper entitled &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.ku.dk/~eilers/lego.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A LEGO Counting problem&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, it's author Søren Eilers proves mathematically that the number of possible combinations is closer to ninety-five-million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both of these cases, tools  which were considered limiting were taken far beyond their perceived capabilities. Perhaps clearly defined boundaries and limitations were what allowed this to happen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently picked up the iPad, it's a curiously limited device. One app a time, full screen, no way to check twitter while I write, no way to switch rapidly between twenty chats and web pages, no distractions. The iPad, more than any device I've used, is defined more by what's missing than what isn't. Yet these missing features are no problem, for many they make the device desirable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm sitting here, typing on glass, music softly playing, nothing else to distract and detract from the simple act of putting words on a screen, and you know what? It's bliss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Limitation breeds creativity.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>